Guide to the Amote Sias papers 2008.017
Brooklyn Historical Society
Amote Sias papers
1945-1993
2008.017
Brooklyn Historical Society
3.0 Linear feet in one manuscript box, one record carton and two oversize flat boxes.
The Amote Sias papers consist of personal essays, legal and financial records, ephemera and various clippings relating to Sias's life and involvement in Brooklyn politics as well as her role as an African-American activist. The majority of the collection focuses on the political environment in Brooklyn from the mid 1970s and 1980s through newspapers, magazines and other publications. The collection is rich with programs, bulletins and manuals from Sias's involvement in various political organizations focusing on social justice, women's rights and Black Nationalism. The collection also documents Sias's political campaign for a seat on the New York City Council in 1989 and her involvement in the Committee to Elect Jesse Jackson for President.
Sias, Amote
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Amote Sias papers were found in Brooklyn Historical Society's collections when the institution reopened in 2004. The materials were subsequently accessioned in 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Arrangement note
The Amote Sias papers are organized into three series: Series 1: Personal Papers; Series 2: Professional Papers; Series 3: Publications and Clippings.
Users of the collection should be aware that folders labeled with a date range might also include undated documents. Oversize materials have been placed in two oversize boxes.
Biographical Note
Amote Sias is a resilient African American social activist who was an active member of the Brooklyn community of Carroll Gardens and a candidate for city office during the 1970s-1980s. Sias is also a deeply committed educator and leader, having been a teacher at both the elementary and secondary level in the New York City Public School system as early as the 1970s. Sias went on to become a renowned principal at the Brooklyn Collegiate High School, a position she continues to hold as of 2010.
Scope and Contents
The Amote Sias papers contain materials concerning Amote Sias and the activist movements she was involved in during the 1970s and 1980s in Brooklyn, New York.
Financial and administrative materials display Amote's involvement in local politics, specifically materials from her campaign for City Council in 1989 as well as her involvement in the Jesse Jackson for President campaign in 1989. Copies of speeches from meetings and example letters to congressmen are also included.
The large number of programs from meetings, lectures and conferences as well as meeting notes and activist paraphernalia provide insight into the active social movements in Brooklyn and across the United States in the late 1970s and 1980s. This collection also documents a variety of the grassroots social organizations active during this timeframe as well as their goals and efforts.
Newspaper and magazine clippings provide a broad framework for viewing the political, economic and social forces surrounding the period in which Sias was politically active. These materials also display the local and national efforts for social justice and equality.
The personal materials in this collection reflect Amote Sias and her role as an educator. Early papers and examples of student work provide insight into the academic work and influences on Sias in the early stages of her career. Various ephemera includes a Girl Scout badge and a Jesse Jackson for President campaign poster.
Congressional Black Caucus.; Democratic National Committee (U.S.).; Jackson, Jesse, 1941-; Jesse Jackson for President '88 Committee.; Madre (Organization).; Sias, Amote; Administrative records; African Americans |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Black nationalism |z United States |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Clippings (information artifacts); Community activists; Correspondence; Financial records; Local elections |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Magazines (periodicals); Manuals (instructional materials); Memorandums; Newspapers; Petitions; Playbills; Political participation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political parties |z United States; political posters; Politicians |z New York (State); Politicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Programs (documents); Social movements |z United States; Voter registration; Voters' lists
- Series 1: Personal Papers, 1971-1980; 0.1 Linear feet
  Arrangement note
  The materials in Series 1 are arranged alphabetically within genre.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 is comprised of examples of essays used for college instruction by Sias, as well as handwritten notes from university lectures and research Sias conducted. Also included is a scrapbook example of a student's work from Sias's time as an teacher in the public school system, autographed theater programs from the plays Bubbling Brown Sugar and Don't Bother Me, I Can't Cope, and a Girl Scout badge.
  - Articles and papers by Sias., 1980 (Box 1, Folder S1:1)
  - Girl Scout badge., undated (Box 1, Folder S1:2)
  - Notes., 1974 (Box 1, Folder S1:3)
  - Autographed playbills., 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder S1:4)
    General note
    Playbills from performances of Bubbling Brown Sugar and Don't Bother Me, I Can't Cope.
  - The World Today scrapbook., 1971 (Box 1, Folder S1:5)
- Series 2: Professional Papers, 1976-1989; 0.9 Linear feet
  Professional Papers contain materials concerning the professional political life of Amote Sias. The bulk of the material in this series surrounds the many facets of the committee to elect Amote Sias to the City Council. Included are the financial records, campaign materials, posters, and signed petitions of support and opposition to her election. Multiple specifications of objections listing the number of valid and invalid signatures from these petitions are also present. Also included are a list of campaign ideas and agendas for committee meetings. Voter guides in English and Spanish for local election in New York City and memos covering voter instructions are also included.
  The series also includes a variety of programs, notes from meetings, and clippings from multiple political conferences, youth educational outreach activities and other social activist and grassroots workshops that Sias had attended and was actively involved in. Copies of speeches from these organizations are also present along with workshop materials and census records. Her involvement in the Jesse Jackson for President campaign can be seen as well as her interaction with the Latin American community in Brooklyn through MADRE. Multiple political organizations are highlighted in this series including the United Nations, the Democratic National Convention and the Congressional Black Caucus.
  The materials in Series 2 are arranged alphabetically within organization or social group. Materials found in box 3 are oversize documents.
  - Black on Black Love Campaign., 1983 (Box 1, Folder S2:1)
  - City Council Election, Committee to Elect Amote Sias (4 folders)., 1989 (Box 1, Folder S2:2-5)
  - Congressional Black Caucus., 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder S2:6)
  - Congressional Black Caucus, Workshop on Political Empowerment, Voter Participation and Network Development., 1984 (Box 1, Folder S2:7)
  - Congressional Districts of the 98th Congress (NY), Population and Housing Census., 1980 (Box 1, Folder S2:8)
  - Democratic National Convention (San Francisco), Guides., 1984 (Box 1, Folder S2:9)
  - Democratic National Committee., 1984 (Box 1, Folder S2:10)
  - Election for Delegate to the Democratic National Convention., 1984 (Box 1, Folder S2:11)
  - Encampment for Citizenship., 1977 (Box 1, Folder S2:12)
  - Jesse Jackson for President Committee., 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder S2:13)
  - Jesse Jackson for President Poster., circa 1984. (Box 3, Folder S2:14)
  - JFK Democratic Club Annual Dinner and Dance, Program., 1976 (Box 1, Folder S2:15)
  - MADRE Delegation., 1985 (Box 1, Folder S2:16)
  - Meeting Notes., undated (Box 1, Folder S2:17)
  - MInority Business Enterprise Legal Defense Fund., undated (Box 1, Folder S2:18)
  - National Black Women's Political Caucus., 1984 (Box 1, Folder S2:19)
  - New York City Community Board, Manuals (2 folders)., 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder S2:20-21)
  - Peace and Enviornmental Convention Coalition., 1984 (Box 1, Folder S2:22)
  - Rivers State of Nigeria., 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder S2:23)
  - Summer Youth Instructional Tennis., 1981 (Box 1, Folder S2:24)
  - UN Conference on Women., 1985 (Box 1, Folder S2:25)
- Series 3: Publications and Clippings, 1945-1993; 2.0 Linear feet
  The materials in Series 3 were arranged alphabetically within publication name. Material designated as housed in box 3 or 4 is oversize material.
  The publications and clippings in this series include a variety of magazine and newspaper articles that Amote Sias collected from the 1970s and 1980s. Publications include both independent activist media sources, as well as mainstream and local newspaper publications. The bulk of the materials are from the United States, especially the greater New York City region, but a few are from Latin American countries and political groups, including Barricada, a Spanish Sandinista newspaper.
  - African Educator, v. 9 n.1., 1985 (Box 2, Folder S3:1)
  - Barricada, Spanish Sandinista Publication., 1985 (Box 3, Folder S3:2)
  - Tony Brown's Journal, 3rd Quarter., 1985 (Box 2, Folder S3:3)
  - Cape Cod Standard-Times., 1974 (Box 3, Folder S3:4)
  - The City Sun., 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder S3:5)
  - Daily News., 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder S3:6)
  - Dallas Times Herald., 1984 (Box 3, Folder S3:7)
  - Delegate (2 folders)., 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder S3:8-9)
  - The Des Moines Register., 1991 (Box 3, Folder S3:10)
  - Folio., 1984 (Box 3, Folder S3:11)
  - Frontline., 1985 (Box 3, Folder S3:12)
  - Future, v. 18-20 (3 folders)., 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder S3:13-15)
  - JCI World, v. 18 n. 2., 1980 (Box 2, Folder S3:16)
  - The Kansas City Star., 1991 (Box 3, Folder S3:17)
  - Mother Jones, v. 9 n. 7., 1984 (Box 2, Folder S3:18)
  - New Amsterdam News., 1984 (Box 3, Folder S3:19)
  - New York Newsday, Brooklyn Voters Guide., 1991 (Box 3, Folder S3:20)
  - New York Post., 1945, 1974 (Box 3, Folder S3:21)
  - New York Times., 1975-1993 (Box 4, Folder S3:22)
  - El Nuevo Diario, Spanish paper., 1985 (Box 4, Folder S3:23)
  - The Star., 1977 (Box 4, Folder S3:24)
  - Street, Issue 14., 1975 (Box 2, Folder S3:25)
  - Sunday Mirror., 1945 (Box 4, Folder S3:26)
  - Unidentified clippings., 1975 (Box 4, Folder S3:27)
  - Various Independent News Media Articles covering the 1984 U.S. Presidential Election. (Box 2, Folder S3:28)
  - The Village Voice., 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder S3:29)